Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series II: Project Proposals
  - Proposal on "Anglican Opportunities in South America," to the Lilly Endowment, Inc., Indiannapolis, submitted jointly by the National Council of the Protestant Epispocal Church and BASR, October, 1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop.279)
  - Proposal on "Determining the Feasibility of a Computer Model of Compulsive Drinking," prepared by William N. McPhee, September,1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 280.)
  - Grant Application to HEW, Public Health Service on "Micro-Analysis Of Disturbed and Therapeutic Communications Processes," from Henry L. Lennard, October 30, 1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 281)
  - David l. Sills and Fred Abrahams An Annotated Outline for the Council of National Organizations Project-"The Governance of Voluntary Associations", May, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 282)
  - Letter concerning possible research on panel date on members of the club to Julie Guttenplan, Columbia Record Club, New York from David L. Sills, December 4,1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 283)
  - Proposal for "A continuation of Research on Latent Structure Analysis," (To?) from BASR, December 8, 1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 284)
  - Specifications for a Contract for Project on "assessing the Performance of Overseas Personnel, to the Peace Corps from BASR, December 20, 1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 285)
  - Letter of Proposal with estimated budget for joint project with Harvard School of Business to relate a number of cases in the Harvard files to currently available knowledge in the social sciences to Mr. Oscar Harkavy, Program in Economic Development and Administration, Ford Foundation, New York, from Paul F. Lazarsfeld, December 21,1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop.286)
  - Proposal for research on "The Social and Psychological Implications of A Program of Construction of Fall-Out Shelters," from Herbert H. Hyman, December,1961 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 287)
  - Application for Research Contract for "A Comparative Study of Interns and Residents,"to Health Research Council of the City of New York, Department of Health, from Clara Shapiro, Administrative Officer, January 29,1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 288)
  - Research Proposal on "Formal Models of Mass Social Processes," submitted to NSF from William N. McPhee, January 26, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.289)
  - Research Proposal on the "Epidemiology of Family Communication, Expectation and Socialization Processes," to NSF, from Henry L. Lennard, January 29, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 290.)
  - Grant Application for study of "Motivation Towards Rehabilitation and its Employment and Other Consequences," to HEW, Office of Vocational Rehabilitation, Washington, D.C., from A.J. Jaffe, January26, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 291.)
  - Research Proposal on "A Study of Methodology of Organization Research," submitted to NSF from Allen H. Barton, January, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.292)
  - Specifications for a Contract on "A Study of the Utilization of Educational Television," to the (Regents Educational Television Project?) from Allen H.Barton, February 12, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 293)
  - Grant Application on "17th.Century Theories of Human Nature," to NIH from Sigmund Diamond, March 5, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 294.)
  - Grant Application to NIH for research on "Cantometrics:Music(Especially Folk Song) as a Psychocultural Indicator," by Alan Lomax from Clara Shapiro, Administrative Officer, March 9, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 295)
  - Letter of Proposal and budget for "A review of studies of Negro Economic Behavior," To Dr. Alfred C. Whitney, Associate Director of Research, Life Insurance Agency Management Association, Hartford, Conn., from Allen H. Barton, March, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.297.)
  - Grant Application on the "Micr-Analysis of Disturbed and Therapeutic Communication Process," to NIH from Henry L. Lennard, April 2, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 298)
  - Grant Application to NIH for research on "Effective Policemen and Effective Police Departments," from Robert Edward Mitchell, April 6, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.299)
  - Letter disscussing possible research on schools and parents to Dr. Robert S. Fleming, Assistant Commissioner of Education, Department of Education, State of New Jersey, Trenton, N. J., from Allen H. Barton, April 10, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 300.)
  - Research Proposal on "public Housing and its Publics," in New York City, for the Citizens' Housing and Planning Council of New York, Inc., under a special grant from the Aaron E. Norman Fund, from David Caplovitz, April, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.301)
  - Proposal for a Survey and Analysis of Specialized Information Sources And Services in the Social Sciences to NSF, Office of Science Information Sources, from Paul F. Lazarsfeld, (1962?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 302.)
  - Grant Application for research on "Health and Demography," to HEW, Public Health Service, from A. J. Jaffe, April 23, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 303)
  - Grant Application for Research on the "Processes of Occupational Choice in Science:The Case of the "Space Cadets," submitted to the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, from Bernard Barber, April,1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 304)
  - Research Proposal for a Pilot Study of Family Communication, Expectation and Socialization Processes,(revision of a proposal entitled Epidemiology of Family Communication, Expectation and Socialization Processes), to NSF from Henry L. Lennard, April, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 305)
  - Letter of Proposal and proposal on the "Success and Failure of International Associations:The British Commonwealth,"toDr, Henry W. Riecken, Social Science Division, National Science Foundation, Washington, D.C., from Allen H.Barton, April, 30,1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 306)
  - Letter of Proposal and budget for eresponse toaddressee on idea of doing a study of Admissions Officers in American Colleges, to Dr. Shildrick A. Kendrick, College Entrance Examination Board, New York, from Allen H. Barton, May 1o, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 307.)
  - Resarch Proposal on Supply and Demand of Middle Level Manpower, especially in underdeveloped parts of the world, to Dr. Silberman of ?, from A.J.Jaffe, May 14, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 308.)
  - Grant Application for Study of "Characteristics of Communications Systems with A Mentally Ill Member," to HEW, Public Health Service, from Henry L.Lennard, May 16, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 309)
  - Letter of Proposal for research into the processes by which large business corporations arrive at decisions as to charitable giving, to Mr. Basil O'Conner, National Foundation, New York, from Allen H. Barton, May 22, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.310)
  - Letter concerning possible work on an evaluation study of your Consumer Action Program for low-income families, to Dr. William Kirk, Union Settlement, New York, from Allen H. Barton, July, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.311)
  - Response concerning possibility of a detailed study of refugees in the United States as suggested by the addressee to the Hon. Phillip A. Hart, United States Senate, Senate Office Buildings, Washington, D.C., from Allen H. Barton, July 5, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.312.)
  - Preliminary Outline of a Study of Higher Education in Latin America from BASR, September 4, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.313)
  - Grant Application to HEW, Social Security Administration, for Study of "The Community Characteristics of Subsidized Housing Projects," from Allen H. Barton, September 14, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.314)
  - Proposal for study of "the image of the Columbia Record Club," submitted to the Columbia Record Club from Fred Abrahams and Rolf Meyersohn, September, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 315)
  - Desc,. Grant Application for "Definition of the Social Worker Role by Groups Essential to Effective Social Work," to HEW, Social Security Administration, from Allen H. Barton, October 1, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop.316)
  - Copies of grant application for "Design of an Evaluation Study of Consumer Education for Low-income Families," for the Social Security Administration, to Mr. William Kirk, Union Settlement Association, New York, from Allen H. Barton, October 5, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 317)
  - Letter of proposal with proposal for a preliminary study of the operation of the disciplinary machinery of the New York Bar, to Professor Ralph S. Brown, Jr., Director, Walter E. Meyer Research Institute of Law ,New Haven Conn., from Jerome E. Carlin, Director, Metropolitan Lawyer Study, October 10, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 318)
  - Letter of proposal and proposal for a Training Program and Seminar In Law and the Bahavioral Sciences to Dean William C. Warren, School of Law, Columbia from Donald Young, November 20, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 319.)
  - Grant Application for "Religion and Psychiatry: A Follow-up Study," to HEW, Public Health Service from Samuel Z. Klausner, February 11, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 320)
  - Proposal for a Columbia Seminar on Sociology and Educational Research, to Orville G. Brim, Jr., Russell Sage Foundation from Sam Sieber, January 4, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 321.)
  - Letter to MR. T. W. Yerzley, Executive Secretary, Office of Projects and Grants, Low Library, concerning grant application for a study on "Relations between Social and Psychological Characteristics of the Arriving Freshman and his Subsequent College Career," for the U.S, January 22, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 322.)
  - Grant Application to the Commissioner of Education, Office of Education, HEW for research on "Further Analysis of Data Collected for the New York State Regents Educational Television Project," from Allen H. Barton, January 28, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 323.)
  - Proposal to NSF for Phase II of Research on Communication, Perception And Social Behavior-through study of Inter-Group relations and Attitudes of the Blind from Herbert H. Hyman, January, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 324.)
  - Proposal for Research on Musical Taste and Repertory Selection to the Columbia Record Club fromFred Abrahams, January,1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 325.)
  - Letter proposing a kind of "Recent Social Trends" project to Dr. Eleanor Sheldon, Russell Sage Foundation from A.J. Jaffe, February 4, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 326)
  - Letter regarding research to be undertaken by Bureau on participation in the New York Academy of Medicine's televised clinical science seminars to Aims C. McGuinness, M.D. from Herbert Menzel, February 9, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 327)
  - Letter with attached proposal "Technological Change and Depressed Areas" to Dr. E.K. Smith, Chief, Economic Analysis Division, Area Redevelopmetn Administration, U.S. Department of Commerce from A.J. Jaffe, February 14, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 328)
  - Letter with attached Department of Health, Education and Welfare proposal form detailing proposed research on payment methods of physicians in 16 countries to Mr. T.W. Yerzley, Executive Secretary, Office of Projects and Grants, Columbia University from Clara Shapiro, February 15, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 329)
  - Letters regarding study of engineering school faculties to Mr. Anson Burlingame, Office of Projects and Grants and Dr. Carl Borgman, Ford Foundation from Clara Shapiro both times, February 21, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 330)
  - Letter with attached Department of Health, Education and Welfare application and financial forms for Career Development Award II to Mr. Thomas Yerzley, Office of Projects and Grants from Clara Shapiro, February 18, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 331)
  - Letter with attached Department of Health, Education and Welfare application form regarding a "corollary research grant approved by National Institute of Mental Health" to Mr. Thomas Yerzel, Office of Projects and Grants from Clara Shapiro, February 19, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 332)
  - Proposal and Department of Health, Education and Welfare application form for the study of "The Military Establishment and Social Change in Venezuela", June 1, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 333)
  - Proposal for study of Consumer Education and Action Program, (1963 ?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 334)
  - Letter regarding proposed seminar on Sociology and the Psychology of Science to Mr. Ellis Mottur, Documentary Research Program, National Science Foundation from Robert K. Merton, Bebruary 5, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 336)
  - Proposal "Possible Types of Research on Effect of Mass Media on Fairnes of Trial" by Rita Simon and Allen Barton, January 25, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 337)
  - Proposal onPatterns of Social and Economic Development in the Modern World from Theodore Caplow, December, 1962 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 338)
  - Proposal for the study of Academic and Business Elites in Portugal from Harry M. Makler, April 17, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 339)
  - Proposal on "Formal and Informal satisfaction of the Information Requirements of Scientists," to the NSF from Herbert Menzel, May, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 340)
  - Proposal on "Technological Change and Depressed Areas,"submitted to the Area Redevelopment Administration, U.S. Department of Commerce from A. J. Jaffe, May, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 341)
  - Copy of Contract with HEW, Public Health Service for research on "Descriptive Analysis of methods of Payment for Physicians Services in Foreign Countries," signed byW.H.Lane,Jr., Controller, Columbia University, April 1, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop.342.)
  - Proposal on a "Cross-Cultural Study of Patients," to NIH, from William A. Glaser, 1963 (?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 343.)
  - Memo study of "The Social Settings of Adult Education," submitted to Mr. Michael Burke, Vice-President, Development, CBS, and Dr. Ormsbee W. Robinson, Director of Educational Affairs, IBM, from BASR, May, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop.344.)
  - Proposal on "International Differences in the Policy Problems of Nursing," to Rockefeller Foundation from BASR, (1963?) (Box 107, Folder Prop.345.)
  - Grant Application for Mental Health Graduate Student Training to NIH from Robert K. Merton, July 30, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 346.)
  - Abstract of Grant Application to Commissioner of Education, Office of Education, HEW for "Further Analysis of Data Collected for the New York State Regents Educational Television Project," from Allen H. Barton, (!963?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 347)
  - Grant Application to Commissioner of Education, Office of Education, HEW for research on "Actual and Perceived Consensus on Educational Goals Between School and Community," from Allen H, Barton, April 1,1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 348.)
  - Proposal on "Determinants of Student Cultures Affecting Academic and Social Conduct," to Low Memorial Library from Allen H, Barton, (1963?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 349)
  - Agreement between Columbia and the Department of Welfare of the City of New York on research on "The Bowery Study-Pilot Phase, !963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 350)
  - Proposal for"A Descriptive Study of the Residents of the East Harlem Triangle," from BASR, Septembeer 20, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 351.)
  - Application for Grant Extension to NIH for "Micro-Analysis of Disturbed and Therapeutic Communication Process," from Henry L. Lennard, July 2, 1963 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 352)
  - Letter requesting grant for supporting the development of "College Characteristic Data Bank,"to Dr.S. A. Kendrick, College Entrance Examination Board, New York, from Allen H. Barton, January 7, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 353)
  - Proposal for further Research and Preparation of a Book on Student Dishonesty, to Russell B. Stearns Foundation, from Director, BASR, January 7, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 354.)
  - Proposal for study of the "Non-Return of Israeli Students, Trainees and Professionals in the United States," from BASR, February 4, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 355)
  - Grant Application to the Behavioral Science Division ,Office of Aerospace Research, US Air Force, D.C. for "Extrapolation of 1,045 Social Science Findings to International Analysis," from Amitai Etzioni, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 356)
  - Proposal for Two Studies on Discovery in Civil Litigation and on the Sociology Of the Litigation Process supported by Ford Foundation and the Walter E, Meyer Institute of Law, Inc., conducted at the request of the Advisory Committee on the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure, noted by Vernon K. Dibble, Associate Director, Project for Effective Justice, Columbia University, April 10, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 357)
  - Proposal for Two Studies on Discovery in Civil Litigation and on The Sociology Of the Litigation Process, submitted to NSF from Vernon K. Dibble, April, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 358.)
  - Proposal for the Study of "Professional Socialization in Two Music Schools," Submitted to NSF from Charles Kadushin, April, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 359.)
  - Proposal for Research on "social Contexts of Beer Drinking," to the United States Brewers Association, Inc., through the J. Walter Thompson Company from Rolf B. Meyersohn, May, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 360)
  - Research Proposal on "Catholic Physicians and Birth Control,"from Herbert H. Hyman and Gene N. Levine, May, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 361)
  - Proposal on "Science for Survival,"-An Inquiry into Public Reactions to the Office of Civil Defense's Exhibit at the 1964 New York World's Fair, submitted to the Office of Civil Defense, Department of the Army, Defense Department, Washington, D.C. from Gene N. Levine and John Modell, August, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 362.)
  - Research Proposal on "College Attendance and the College Trained Population," submitted to the U.S. Commissioner ofr Education, Washington, D.C., by A.J.Jaffe, August 24, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 363.)
  - Grant Application to HEW, Public Health Service, on research Concerning an "Inventory of Propositions in Sociopharmacology," from Hernry L. Lennard, February 28, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 364.)
  - Research Proposal on "The Making of a Devaint:The Puerto Rican School Drop-Out," submitted to the Commissioner of Education, Washington, D.C., from Samuel E. Wallace, December 1, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop.365.)
  - Research Proposal on "Scientific and Technical Communication in the Professions-A Proposal to Integrate Research," to (Columbia?), from Herbert Menzel, November 24, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 366.)
  - Research proposal on "College Enrollment Projections to 1975 and 1980, on the Basis of a New Census Survey," to the U.S. Commissioner of Education from A. J. Jaffe, November 24, 1964 (Box 107, Folder Prop.367.)
  - Research Proposal on "Further Analysis ana a Report to the Legal Profession on the Columbia Study of Pretrial Discovery and the Adversarial Process," to the Russell Sage Foundation from the Columbia Project for Effective Justice, Columbia School of Law and BASR, (1964?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 368.)
  - Grant Application to HEW, Public Health Service, on "A Study Of Interpersonal Violence," from Samuel E. Wallace, January 4, 1965 (Box 107, Folder Prop.369.)
  - Grant Application on 'The making of a Deviant: The Puerto Rican School Drop-Out," to HEW, Social Security Administration, from Samuel E. Wallace, (1965?) (Box 107, Folder Prop.370.)
  - Proposal on "Inventory in the Field of Family," to? from William J.Goode., (File Folder-only Copy), (1965?) (Box 107, Folder Prop. 371.)
  - Propsal for the "Study of Family Structures and Mobility Processes," Submitted to the NSF, Washington, D.C., from William J. Goode, January 1,1965 (Box 107, Folder Prop. 372.)
  - Proposal entitled "Study of Public Health Nursing Field Experience in the Program of the Cornell University-New York Hospital School of Nursing" by William Glaser, December 20, 1958 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 198)
  - Proposal for the "Study of Family Structures and Mobility Processes," submitted to NSF, from William J. Goode, January 1,1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.373.)
  - Proposal for "A Program For Evaluation of Haryou-Act," Submitted to Harlem Youth opportunities Unlimited and Associated Community Teams from BASR, January 12, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 374.)
  - Research Proposal on the "Civil Service and Politics: The Development of Relationships Between Two Political Institutions," to? from William A. Glaser, December 1, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.375.)
  - Proposal for study of "Family Sructures and Mobility Processes," to? from William J. Goode, (See File for Only Copy, ` (1965?) (Box 108, Folder Prop.376.)
  - Proposal for a "Program of Basic Research in the Sociology of Science," to the NSF from Robert K. Merton, February 1, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.377.)
  - Proposal on "Measures of Outcome of Poverty Programs," to be submitted to the Office of Economic Opportunities,(HEW?), from Allen H. Barton, February 23, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.378.)
  - Grant Application for "A Theoretical Analysis of the Problem of Privacy," to HEW, Public Health Service, from Allen H. Barton, February,26, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.379.)
  - Research proposal on "Campus Social Climates and Student Misconduct," to the Commissioner of Education, Office of Education, HEW, from William J. Bowers, February 26,1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.380.)
  - Proposal on "Problems of Data Collection From Low-Income Populations," to be submitted to the Welfare Administration of HEW from BASR, December 22, 1964 (Box 108, Folder Prop.381.)
  - Proposal and (Grant Application?) for research on an "Extrapolation of 1,045 Social Science Findings to International Analysis," to the Advanced Research Projects Agency, Washington, D.C., from Amitai Etzioni, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.382.)
  - Proposal for study of "Population, Employment and Economic Change in Selected Underdeveloped Countries," submitted to the Office of Technical Cooperation and Research, Agency for International Development, Washington, D.C., from A. J. Jaffe, (May 1,1965?) (Box 108, Folder Prop.383.)
  - Proposal on "The Lavenberg Project Demonstration Study," submitted by BASR, (1965?) (Box 108, Folder Prop.384.)
  - Proposal for Research on "Effects of the Harlem Neighborhood Legal Assistance Project," to be submitted to the Office of Economic Opportunity, Washington, D.C. by David Caplovitz and Barbara Rubin, (1965?) (Box 108, Folder Prop. 385)
  - Proposal and budget for "Application of the Theory of compliance to Social Work Administration," to (HEW?), from Amitai Etzioni, (1965?) (Box 108, Folder Prop. 386.)
  - Proposal for a Study of the Supply of Students for Negro Colleges to? From A. J. Jaffe, March 18, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 387)
  - Proposal for "A Study of the Development of Computer programs for Social Science Data Analysis," submitted to NSF from Charles Kadushun, December 15, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 388.)
  - Proposal for the Study of Methodological Problems in Survey Research to? from BASR, June 25, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.389.)
  - Prelim. Proposal letter on "The NEW European Worker," to either Carnegie, Ford, or Rockefeller Foundations from William Glaser and Juan Linz, May 18, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 390.)
  - Proposal on "The Measurement of Hidden Unemployment," to the Area Redevelopment Administration, U.S. Department of Commerce, Washington, D.C., from A. J. Jaffe, April 28, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 391.)
  - Proposal on "The Demography of the Middle Years," to ?, from A. J. Jaffe, May 3,1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop. 392.)
  - Proposal to "Study the Performance of Vista Volunteers in the Field," submitted to VISTA by BASR, May 18, 1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.393.)
  - Proposal for the "Methodological Analysis of Testimony as a Source of Data In History and Social Science," to NSF from Vernon K. Dibble, June ,1965 (Box 108, Folder Prop.394)